[Music]
it sounds like science fiction bacteria
in a vial of dirt taken from a
mysterious island create a compound that
prolongs life and not just in the
traditional medical sense thanks to
advances in modern medicine we're living
longer lives but we're doing so by
lengthening the morbidity phase in other
words we're living longer but sicker
lives traditional medical approaches
tend to just increase the number of old
people in bad Health ideally though we'd
extend lifespan by slowing aging that
way we could delay the onset of
deterioration rather than just extend
the period of
deterioration that's exactly what this
new compound appeared to do researchers
called it rapamycin named after the
bacteria's home the mystical Easter
Island famed for its Rock carved figures
which is known locally as rapanui
rapamycin inhibits an enzyme that's come
to be known as mtor or mechanistic
Target of rapamycin a key modulator of
Aging characterized as a master
determinant of lifespan and aging what
does the enzyme mtor actually do it's
the major regulator of growth in animals
activation of mtor drives increases in
both cell size and cell number what's
wrong with that the action of mtor has
been described as is the engine of a
speeding car without
brakes this analogy aging is a hurdling
car that enters the low speed zone of
adulthood and damages itself because it
does not and cannot slow down we are
over the hill and picking up
speed why don't living organisms have
breakes because they've never needed
them in the wild animals often don't
live long enough to experience aging
most animals die before they even reach
adulthood the same used to be true for
humans due to early age mortality in the
17th century most londoners didn't even
make it to age
16 so living beings need to grow as fast
as possible to start reproduction before
they die from external causes the best
evolutionary strategy May therefore be
to run at full speed however once we
pass the Finish Line once we win the
race to pass on our genes we're still
careening forward at an unsustainable
Pace all thanks to this enzyme mtor in
our childhood mtor is an engine of
growth but in adulthood it can be
thought of as the engine of Aging nature
simply selects for the brightest flame
which in turn casts the darkest
Shadow this is the so-called tradeoff
Theory of Aging a concept technically
known as antagonist IC pleotropic in
which a gene can have a positive effect
when young but a negative effect when
old this explains how genes with
delerious effects late in life can
persist in a population for example the
pro-inflammatory Alzheimer's Gene
appears to protect against childhood
infections a major killer throughout
most of human existence what's the
downside of unconstrained growth fueled
by mtor the enzyme plows full seem ahead
revving up construction Pathways to
churn out cellular building blocks for
New Growth which can include cancerous
tumors while cancelling any renovation
or
demolition to preserve growth at all
costs mtor actively suppresses autophagy
countermanding cellular cleansing and
Rejuvenation in my autophagy chapter and
how not to age I explain how this can
lead to accelerated aging conversely
slowing things down by putting the
brakes on mtor appears to decelerate the
aging process extending life and health
inhibiting mtor is considered the best
validated aging regulator
[Music]